Good ערב טוב *erev tov* everybody. We pick up today on דף
daf ע״ח *daf ayin chet*, 78.
Let's read pick it up from the משנה Mishna *mishna*. We have
been dealing with cases about limbs of sacrifices and sacrifices getting mixed
up. Our משנה Mishna *mishna* deals with when the bloods of sacrifices
get mixed up and it's a very really like one of a
major סוגיא *sugya* that connects to broader discussions of ביטול bitul. *bittel*,
of of course when you know foods that are forbidden get mixed
up, a drop of חזיר chazir *chazir* soup falls into your chicken
soup or something of that nature. So משנה Mishna *mishna* on the
bottom of ע״ז עמוד ב׳ *ayin zayin amud bet* says, דם שנתערב
במים dam she'nisarev be'mayim *dam shenitarev bemayim*, if a drop of blood
of a sacrifice gets mixed up in water. So normally when you
want the thing that falls in to get you want it to
become בטל batel. *battel*, you want it to lose its identity, you
want the חזיר chazir *chazir* drop of חזיר chazir *chazir* soup to
be considered not present so you can have your chicken soup. But
here you want the blood to be considered present so that you
can put it on the altar. So אם יש בו מראה דם
כשר kosher *im yesh bo mareh dam kasher*, if it has the
appearance of blood, if there's still a redness to the water. And
again the question here is what does it mean appearance of blood.
If through its appearance you can detect there's blood there or does
it mean that the actual mixture looks like blood? That obviously would
require a lot more blood. It sounds like more of the former
but it's not I think sufficiently clarified. Anyway if you can let's
say it's there's some appearance of blood there, it's considered that it's
present and you can put it on the altar. The interesting thing
is when it comes to food, the core criteria is טעם ta'am
*taam*, taste. If it can be tasted, if you can still taste
some חזיר chazir *chazir* in the chicken soup then it's present, if
it can't be tasted it's not present. Here it goes by the
way it looks. And as I said yesterday, one of the reasons
is because our primary sense that we use for for
interpreting getting information about the world, interpreting the world or whatever has
to do with sight. And how things look and so on. That's
our primary way of
of knowing the world and of categorizing the world. So therefore it
makes sense that something would go by sight. How does it look
determines whether it's present or not, unless you're actually dealing with something
you're going to eat then you're going to want to know how
it tastes. So when it comes to mixtures of food, the presence
of taste is significant and that's also a principle of טעם כעיקר
ke'ikkar *taam ke-ikar* that we say the taste of something of something
forbidden is like the thing itself. But when it comes to things
that are not about foods, the issue and this could be about
blood on the altar, that could be about water to use for
a מקוה mikvah *mikvah*, other types of things, where the question about
is something present or not goes by the way it looks not
by the way it tastes. And that's a very important principle number
one. On the one hand part of a general discussion of ביטול
bitul *bittel*, and on the other hand the factor used the you
know the litmus test is appearance here and not taste. Okay so
if it has the appearance of blood it is still כשר kosher
*kasher*. נתערב ביין Nitarev b'yayin *nitarev beyayin*, let's say it gets mixed
up with wine. So now you can't tell because it's all dark
and red and whatever. רואין אותו כאילו הוא מים Ro'in oto k'ilu
hu mayim *ro'inu oto ke'ilu hu mayim*, you look at the wine
as if it's water. Okay see that we turned wine into water.
Maybe we'll turn water into wine. We'll have to see. You look
at the wine as if it's water and if there is a
and if you say had it been water if the blood would
be visible, therefore the blood is still present and I can put
it on the altar. That's also strange because we're being lenient. We're
allowing you to put the blood on the altar and say the
sacrifice is good even though the blood is not detectable. We're doing
it because hypothetically it would be detectable were this to be water.
Now again in the normal world of ביטול bitul *bittel* and about
foods, this would be a concept of like מין במינו min bemino,
*min be-mino* and מין בשאינו מינו min b'sheino mino, *min be-she'eino mino*.
And you know if something would fall if a drop of טרפה
*treif* chicken soup would fall like you שחט *shechted* the chicken incorrectly
would fall into kosher chicken soup, so then we would be strict
and we would say well had this been חזיר chazir *chazir* it
would have been tasted even though it can't be tasted now because
it's chicken and chicken, it's still going to be a problem. So
we would do the same. We would say what would be this
like if this were חזיר chazir *chazir*, if this were something different
rather than something the same. Okay but there the result is that
we're going to be strict, there it's a rabbinic rule, biblically if
it's all the same it's בטל batel. *battel* by majority. But because
we say had it been different it would have been able to
taste it, had it been חזיר chazir *chazir* I could have been
tasted it, it's going to be forbidden now. That's a rabbinic stringency
because we know that because really technically now it can't be tasted
and it should be okay. That one minute that's in the חזיר
chazir, *chazir* in soup case. But in the case of but that's
a rabbinic stringency. Here we're doing the opposite. We're being lenient. We're
saying even though it cannot be seen and logically it should already
be בטל batel. *battel*, since at a different
hypothetical mixture it would have been visible, the blood is still present
and we can still use it. So this certainly suggests that the
idea that מין במינו min bemino *min be-mino* we treat it as
if it's אינו מינו Eino mino *eino mino* could even have be
based on a biblical concept that we'd say that even though now
it's not visible and detectable, since at a different hypothetical mixture it
would be, that is enough to consider it to still be present.
So that's a very big חידוש chiddush. *chiddush* that we are using
this to be lenient. Fine, that's about visible versus tastable, but the
concept still is now it's not visible or tastable or whatever, should
be בטל, batel, had it been a different type of mixture would
have been detectable, okay, and here it sounds like even to be
lenient we would say that you're still present. So that's a very
big חידוש. chiddush Charlie you wanted to say?
Yeah, it doesn't specifically say red wine.
That's the assumption. If it doesn't say יין לבן, yayin lavan, you
assume it's red wine. Okay. Now, נתערב בדם בהמה בדם חולין, nitarav
bedam behemah bedam chulin, okay, let's say it gets mixed up with
blood that cannot be put, that is not,
that's also blood, excuse me, blood and blood. So also you can't
detect if it's there, okay, either because it's a non-sanctified animal or
בדם החיה, bedam hachayah, or it's an animal that's a deer whatever.
Same point, רואהו כאילו הוא מים. ro'ehu ke'ilu hu mayim. So of
course logically same thing. If you could do it with wine, you
could do it with blood. You view it as if it's water
and if it would be detectable, you can go ahead and use
it. Top of עין ח עמוד א. ayin chet amud alef. This
is all a חזרה chazarah from yesterday but might as well so
short דף today. רבי יהודה אומר אין דם מבטל דם. Rabbi Yehudah
omer ein dam mevatel dam. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah says no, no,
here I'm going to be stricter. And here I'm going to say
wine and blood I'll say had it been detectable in water the
blood is present and use it. Blood and blood I'm going to
say actually, excuse me, not stricter, more lenient, keep on forgetting which
way it go. Blood, if
so if it's a drop of blood in a lot of wine,
you the rabbis will say that had that wine been water the
blood would have completely, you know, dissipated or whatever and it wouldn't
be detectable you can't use it. Okay, so clearly for the rabbis
they're being to some degree lenient, they're saying we look at the
wine as if it's water, but there's a point after which the
blood is בטל. batel There is so much wine and such little
blood that the blood is בטל. batel. Similarly they would say there
could be so much of the deer blood and such little of
the קרבן korban blood that the blood would be בטל. batel. רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehudah is being lenient. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah this
is the principle of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah that מין במינו לא
בטל. min bemino lo batel. If it's really the same thing, blood
and blood, not just it looks the same, blood and wine, it's
really the same blood and blood, then there's no concept of ביטול.
bitul The logic behind this is that for to be מבטל mevatel
something it requires difference. You have to say there's blood and wine,
there's so much more wine that there's no longer any blood here.
Okay, that I would agree. And if there's enough wine, you know,
the blood is no longer present. But blood and blood you can't
say there's so much blood there's no longer any blood here. Okay.
So even though one is the blood you want, the blood of
a קרבן, korban, and one is the blood that you don't want,
the blood of a deer, nevertheless there's no difference. And because there's
no difference between the mixtures, you can't say the blood of the
קרבן korban disappears. At the end of the day it's all blood,
so the blood is always present. So even though it's only present
in small proportions, it's always present. So whereas the rabbis say, so
we have leniency number one that everybody agrees to, blood and wine
you don't just say it all looks the same and it's בטל,
batel you say had the wine been water, if the blood would
still be visible, it's still present and you can use it. So
that's leniency one: you look at the wine as if it's water.
But then רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah has leniency number two. רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehudah says, and they would also say you look at the
blood as water, that's what the חכמים chachamim say. And רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehudah says okay, but there's a point after which you guys
are going to say it's בטל batel because the blood would no
longer be visible. I'm going to say if it's all blood it's
not בטל. batel. If it's all the same stuff, it's always present.
Yes, Charlie.
So specifically by רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah
we have a situation where ordinarily we would get a stringency but
here we're getting a leniency.
Right, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah is very stringent in laws of כשרות
kashrut and it's a big leniency in laws of קרבנות. korbanot. Okay.
Now leniency meaning because you
can still throw it on the altar.
No, I thought if you since it's not מבטל mevatel then you
have all this דם חיה dam chayah there which you can't...
No, no, you're not trying to be מבטל mevatel the חיה. chayah.
You don't care. Put some חיה chayah blood on the altar. Why
wouldn't I care? Because we don't. The question
is, is the קרבן korban blood still present? If the קרבן korban
blood is still present, then you can throw the mixture on the
altar and be יוצא yotzei your קרבן. korban. So the point is
we want the קרבן korban blood to be present.
I still don't understand why they ask how many,
be חולין בעזרה, chulin ba'azarah, anyway, whatever you know that's so irrelevant.
נתערב בדם פסולים, nitarav bedam psulim, if it gets mixed up in
blood of invalid sacrifices, accidentally the blood of a בעל מום, ba'al
mum, ישפך לאמה. yishafech la'amah.
Even if we would normally say the blood is still present because
the proportions are right according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah it's always
present, we don't want the blood of invalid sacrifices on the altar.
Again, we don't mind if it's the blood of a deer on
the altar, but we do mind if it's the blood of invalid
sacrifices. We'll have to see why. So you spill it into the
drain. בדם התמצית, bedam hatamtzit, similarly if it's blood that's not the
life blood of an animal, the blood that comes out after the
initial squirting, also even if it was from a קרבן, korban, ישפך
לאמה, yishafech la'amah, spill it into the drain. So why there even
though you could fulfill your sacrifice because the original blood is still
seen as present we don't want you to do it? We'll talk
about in the גמרא. Gemara. But רבי אליעזר מכשיר. Rabbi Eliezer machshir.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer by the way says no that's okay. Maybe
he would agree by the case of an invalid sacrifice don't לכתחילה
lechatchilah put it on the altar, but of this non-life blood that's
okay and therefore your קרבן korban can be good.
Go ahead wait, we say יש ישפך לאמה yishaphech la'amah and then
you're
not יוצא yotzeh your קרבן. korban.
If you still can, like if you could.
אם לא נמלך ונתן כשר. Im lo nimlach venatan kasher. If however
you didn't ask permission, like we said before, sometimes it's easier to
ask forgiveness than to ask for permission. Okay, so if you didn't
ask permission then and you went ahead and you did throw it
on the altar, it's good, because the principle is still the same,
the blood is not בטל. batel For whatever reason rabbinically in this
case where it's not life blood or blood of פסולים, psulim, we
didn't want you putting it on the altar, okay, but if you
did, the blood of the כשר kosher קרבן korban was not בטל
batel and you had fulfilled your קרבן. korban. Let's take a look
now at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so as you can see, really
interesting stuff in terms of mixtures and ביטול bitul. and so on.
אמר ר' חייא בר אבא, Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, said ר'
חייא בר אבא, Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, אמר ר' יוחנן, Amar Rabbi
Yochanan, name ר' יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, לא שנו אלא שנפלו מים לתוך
דם. lo shanu ela shenaflo mayim le-toch dam. This he is assuming
that this stuff fell like drop by drop, the mixture of blood
and water. So he says, or when would this be true, if
the water fell into the blood. Drop, drop, drop, drop, water falling
into the blood, eventually there's a ton of water, a little bit
of blood. The blood is not בטל batel. if it can still
be visible. אבל נפל דם לתוך מים, Aval nafal dam le-toch mayim,
if the blood fell into the water, and it fell drop by
drop, so the first drop of blood that fell in, it was
not visible at all. And therefore it was בטל. batel. Next drop
falls in, still not visible. After twenty drops have fallen in, now
all of a sudden the water looks a little reddish. So in
that case he says that even though now it's red, since with
the first nineteen drops it wasn't visible, those first nineteen drops were
already בטל batel, and they don't stop being בטל batel. even though
now it becomes reddish again. It's not what our משנה Mishna sounds
like. Our משנה Mishna doesn't say how they got mixed up. One
minute Michael. Okay, אבל נפל דם לתוך מים ראשון ראשון בטל. aval
nafal dam le-toch mayim rishon rishon batel.
The first drop, drop, drop is בטל. batel? Now it's not what
our משנה Mishna, sounds like because our משנה Mishna also doesn't sound
like it's drop by drop. Our משנה Mishna's just sounds like the
total amount of blood you're going to be dealing with and the
total amount of water you're going to be dealing with mixed up,
and therefore in that case it doesn't matter which fell into which,
because if the whole mixture happened at once and it was visible
then it was never בטל. batel, So he actually is imagining a
case, so I'm not bothered that this isn't in the משנה, mishnah
because you're right, the משנה mishnah doesn't distinguish which way, but the
משנה's Mishnah. also the פשט pshat is assuming it all got mixed
up at once. He's imagining a different scenario where it was drop,
drop, drop. If you want to talk about that scenario, you can
distinguish between the order that it fell. And therefore what he says
is if the initial drops become בטל, batel. then even though after
a while they now are visible again, the ביטול bitul. already took
place and it doesn't stop being בטל. batel. Now this is a
principle in הלכה halacha called חוזר וניעור. chozer venaiur. Does it come
back and wake up again? Okay, like a sleeper cell, it's sleeping
and then it has to be activated again. So normally we do
say something is חוזר וניעור. chozer venaiur. Let me give you an
example. You have your pot of chicken soup and you have little
drops of חזיר chazir, soup falling in. Drop, and it's very tiny,
it's one in a... you know, one in two hundred. Okay, so
and it can't be tasted. Drop, now it's only one in a
hundred, can't be tasted. Drop, oh, now it's one in fifty, the
three drops together, now all of a sudden you can taste it,
or whatever, after ten drops you can taste it, okay.
Would we say, oh, it's no problem, it's all כשר because it
all... the first drops became בטל? batel, No, we would normally say
חוזר וניעור. chozer venaiur. It reawakens it, now the חזיר chazir? can
be tasted, okay, and now it's a problem. So that is actually
normally we do say that, and we're going to see in a
minute we'll say this here also in a different scenario, but the
reason it's going to seem in a second that we don't say
it here is because of the principle of דיחוי. dichui. So since
those initial drops of blood for a period were בטל, batel, they
were נדחה. nidcha. They were now pushed away. And we know by
a sacrifice once something is pushed off and can't be used, it
cannot become now fit to be used again. So even though what
he's really going to say, which will be clarified in מנחות Menachot
nine, is even though we normally would say חוזר וניעור, chozer venaiur,
it would be reactivated now that the proportions are different, okay, but
by sacrifices this doesn't work because the blood has already been pushed
away. So let's see how the גמרא's Gemara's going to say that,
not by a case of איסור, issur, of drops of חזיר chazir.
into chicken soup where as I said if the drops would accumulate
it would be a problem, but even by an area of מצוות,
mitzvot, okay. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, ולעניין כיסוי אינו כן.
ule-inyan kisui eino ken. Let's say this was a case about כיסוי
הדם, kisui hadam, okay, about the covering of blood, okay, that let's
say you slaughtered an animal and the blood spilled on the ground
and you have to cover it, and now somehow... it's funny because
you're imagining you've got to cover it in the place where it
fell or whatever, I have to sort of think about a scenario.
Let's say
the
blood was rolled off a cliff and started dripping into a puddle
of water below, okay, drop, drop, drop, okay, and in that... so
you could do כיסוי הדם kisui hadam where the blood is falling
off of the edge of the cliff, okay, you've got to... okay,
but there, drop, it wasn't visible, drop, it wasn't visible, drop, it
wasn't visible. Now after ten drops it's visible. You can do כיסוי
הדם kisui hadam on that mixture below, even though after the first
nine drops, the first nine drops had already become בטל. batel. Why?
Why can you do that? Because he said לפי שאין דיחוי במצוות
lefi she'ein dichuy be'mitzvos because the fact that those first nine drops
first weren't able to be used for a מצווה mitzvah does not
total the idea that something is pushed away from a מצווה mitzvah
and can't be reused again we don't say. If something happened to
my תפילין tefillin or whatever my ציצית, tzitzis, I fixed it or
whatever, we never say oh it's נדחה, nidcheh, you can no longer
use this object. That's an idea that we say by קרבנות, korbanos,
we don't say it by מצוות. mitzvos. So even though the blood,
the first nine drops were in a state of ביטול bitul, and
were in a state that they couldn't be have the act of
כיסוי הדם kisui hadam done to it, once that tenth drop fell
in and it became visible and it became the blood became present
again, oh, so the blood had disappeared for a while, now it
became present again, okay, we don't care about נדחה, nidcheh, now it's
present, now we can do it. And the same by the drops
when you're dealing with איסור, issur, the drops of the חזיר chazir,
and the chicken soup. The חזיר chazir had disappeared for a while
because it was tiny proportions. Now there's enough חזיר Chazer that can
be tasted, the חזיר Chazer? reappears, it's present, you can't eat the
chicken soup. The only place it can't work is by קרבנות korbanos
because by קרבנות korbanos even though the blood has reappeared, since it
had disappeared for a while, it's נדחה nidcheh and can't be used.
Okay, so the basic principle here is like the opposite of what
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was saying. The general rule is חוזר וניעור
chozer ve'ne'or that when the proportions grow so that now it's detectable,
it does become a problem or it does become present. The exception
is קרבן korban because of the concept of נדחה. nidcheh. Okay, there
was a question here. Yes.
I was gonna say just
רבי יוחנן'ס Rabbi Yochanan's case was you know drop depends which goes
into which, but all I was trying to say is this is
דם שנתערב במים but also let's say מים שנתערבו בדם. mayim she'nisarvu
be'dam. So I don't know if you can tell which is going
into what based on that. That's all I was trying to say.
Like can you infer anything from the way our משנה Mishnah is?
No, but it doesn't matter. Our משנה Mishnah was talking that they
all got mixed up at the same time as I was saying.
Okay, אמר ריש לקיש. Amar Reish Lakish. So that's point number one.
Now we go on to a statement about as we'll see another
statement about ביטול. bitul. הפגול והנותר והטמא. Ha'pigul ve'ha'nosar ve'ha'tamei. You have
three different איסורים. issurim. Okay, he's like in the since we're in
זבחים Zevachim we're in the world of קרבנות, korbanos, but you could've
said, you know, I don't know, חזיר, Chazer נבילה neveilah and I
don't know something else חלב. chelev. Okay, right. Okay, שבללן זה בזה.
she'bilalan zeh be'zeh. You mixed them all together. You put them in
your blender. Vroom! Okay, now you got this nice—he's joining in with
the sounds now. Right, exactly. Now you well I guess we're talking
about things being visible so I'm switching to sounds, I don't know
anyway. Now you've got this nice shake here of a third of
a third of פגול, pigul, a third of נותר nosar and a
third of טמא. tamei. Three separate איסורים, issurim, pretty weighty איסורים, issurim,
they're all like כרת. karet.
Okay,
and—this is like a קרבן טמא, korban tamei, right? Yeah.
Okay, ואכלן ve'achalan and you ate them, פטור, patur, you're exempt. Why?
אי אפשר שלא ירבה מין על חברו ויבטלנו. Ee efshar she'lo yarbeh
min al chaveiro ve'yvatlenu. It's impossible that one species, one type of
איסור issur does not increase over the other and cause ביטול. bitul
Now there's as you could see a huge תוספות, Tosafos, a big
רש"י Rashi to try to explain what this means. I have to
tell you, and part of what's bothering them is the גמרא Gemara
is going to say שמע מינה תלת shema mina telat and one
of the three things doesn't exactly match up. But before you get
to the שמע מינה תלת. shema mina telat. The פגול pigul had
to overcome טמא, tamei, טמא tamei had to—no no, don't—no don't worry.
Now but before we get to those three things, let me tell
you what I think the פשט pshat is, although neither רש"י Rashi
or תוספות Tosafos says this because it doesn't fit with one of
the three things we're going to learn from this. But the פשט
pshat of this is very simple. The פשט pshat of this is,
okay, you know, let's take my example: חזיר, Chazer? נבילה neveilah and
חלב chelev or whatever it is, okay, or חמץ בפסח, chametz be'Pesach,
whatever. So you mix them all up and you have those things.
Now you eat this. Okay, let's even eat it all at once.
All right? Which עבירה aveirah did you do? Pick an עבירה aveirah
that you think I did.
All three of them.
No, just pick one at a time. Okay, did I do חמץ?
chametz?
You ate something אסור. assur.
No, I didn't do חמץ. chametz. You know why I didn't do
חמץ? chametz? Because two thirds of that mixture was non-חמץ. chametz. Did
I eat נבילה? neveilah? No, because two thirds of that mixture was
non-נבילה. neveilah. Did I eat חזיר? Chazer No, because two thirds of
that mixture was non-חזיר. Chazer And therefore even though I've got three
איסורים issurim in my mouth, okay, each one is מבטל mevatel the
other one and you can't point to any particular עבירה aveirah that
I have done.
But you go by רוב. rov.
What? This is assuming ביטול ברוב. bitul be'rov. Okay? We're assuming ביטול
ברוב. bitul be'rov. So assuming ביטול ברוב, bitul be'rov, the same way
if two thirds had been כשר and one third had been טריף,
treif, that would do ביטול, bitul, okay, even if they're different איסורים,
issurim, they create ביטול. bitul Okay? So that is a big חידוש
chiddush because you would think it's one thing when you're dealing with
היתר heter and איסור issur that the function of ביטול Bittul is
that the predominance of היתר heter eliminates the status of איסור. issur.
It is funnier to say that we, you know, it's sort of
like the principle I always tell you about Aristotle about the about
the excluded middle. It's not like the world is made up of
chocolate and vanilla, it's made up of chocolate and non-chocolate. Okay? So
you don't need איסור issur and היתר. heter. You don't need היתר
heter to be מבטל mevatel איסור. issur. If you have איסור issur
X and things that are not איסור issur X, and you have
נבילה neveilah and non-נבילה, neveilah, the two thirds non-נבילה neveilah is מבטל
mevatel נבילה. neveilah. The two thirds non-חמץ chametz is מבטל mevatel the
חמץ. chametz. Okay, so... That is a big חידוש chiddush. that you
don't need היתר heter to be מבטל mevatel איסור. issur. Fine, we're
talking about רוב. rov. We're not going to worry about taste, we'll
get to that in a minute. But that's not the basic חידוש.
chiddush The basic חידוש chiddush is you don't need היתר, heter, okay?
And that's the first שמע מינה. shma mina. So the גמרא Gemara
says שמע מינה תלת. shma mina tlat. From this you infer three
things. שמע מינה איסורין מבטלין זה את זה. shma mina issurin mevatlin
zeh et zeh. You don't, even if it's not היתר, heter, even
if it's different איסורים, issurim, they can be מבטל mevatel one
another. What? It's all meat. We're going to say, the גמרא's Gemara
going to get to it, the גמרא's Gemara eventually going to say
it's all מין במינו, Min be-mino it's all meat. So don't use
my חמץ chometz example, okay? Whatever you say, okay? It's all meat.
It's a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, נבילה, neveilah, and חזיר, Chazer okay?
It's all meat, or it all tastes the same. I don't know
if חזיר's Chazer good because maybe it tastes different. Doesn't matter, it's
all the same. That's why his example is better, because his example
is פיגול, pigul, נותר, notar, and טמא, tamei, and those are all
three types of meat. Okay, so if we want to keep with
him, פיגול, pigul, נותר, notar, and טמא, tamei, all types of meat.
That's why we don't care about taste. It's all the same, so
you just need רוב. rov. Okay, so big חידוש chiddush number one
is איסורין מבטלין זה את זה. issurin mevatlin zeh et zeh. You
don't need היתר, heter, alright? Even if there were איסורים, issurim, they
can be מבטל mevatel one another. איסורין מבטלין זה את זה. issurin
mevatlin zeh et zeh. ושמע
מינה, ushma mina, and you heard from this, נותן טעם ברוב לאו
דאורייתא. noten ta'am berov lav d'oraisa. Even if it gives taste, as
long as you've got a majority it's not a problem. So at
this stage the גמרא Gemara assumes that it gives taste. At this
stage the גמרא Gemara assumes that they're different things, okay? Which is
funny, how would you have פיגול, pigul, נותר, notar, and טמא? tamei?
Those all apply to meat. So the גמרא Gemara is going to
correct that, okay? Or the גמרא Gemara at this stage maybe doesn't
understand that there's a difference between מין במינו Min be-mino and מין
בשאינו min beshe'eino... מינו, Mino whether it's the same or not. But
the גמרא Gemara is saying here what's clear for you, רייש לקיש,
Reish Lakish, is that you care about majority and majority creates ביטול,
Bittul the majority of one thing creates ביטול bittul over the other,
and we don't care about it being able to be tasted. Now
the גמרא's Gemara going to challenge that and the גמרא's Gemara going
to say of course we care about it being able to be
tasted, this is a case where it can't be tasted because it's
all meat, it's the same
meat, meaning it's all lamb meat.
Right, right, correct, okay, so right.
So anyway at this stage the גמרא Gemara thinks that you're telling
us a big חידוש chiddush that we don't care about taste. In
the end we're going to bracket that and say no we do
care about taste, it's just that they all taste the same here.
The real חידוש chiddush was point number one, okay? And here becomes
חידוש chiddush number three: ושמע מינה התראת ספק לא שמה התראה. ushma
mina hatra'at safek lo shemah hatra'ah. That a doubtful warning doesn't count
as a warning. And this is what gets רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafot so confused, not confused, that's not whatever, but so like challenges
so much in interpreting the case in the גמרא. Gemara. Because the
example I just gave you has nothing to do with התראה, hatra'ah,
it has nothing to do with warning, okay? The reality
is there's no פיגול, pigul, there's no נותר, notar, there's no טמא
tamei because everything is מבטל mevatel everything else. So what do you
mean התראת ספק? hatra'at safek? Where's the doubt, okay? So now you
could say the גמרא Gemara just sort of means that more like
metaphorically, okay? Because notice, by the way, רייש לקיש Reish Lakish doesn't
say you don't get lashes. He says פטור. patur. פטור patur could
even mean like פטור מקרבן. patur mikorban. The things he dealt with
were חיוב חטאת. chiyuv chatas. So the whole idea of התראת ספק
hatra'at safek is a discussion by lashes. So I'd rather interpret the
גמרא Gemara metaphorically. I'd rather interpret the גמרא Gemara saying even though
we know there are times where you really do an איסור, issur,
but you're not going to get punished because we weren't able to
be warned for it: התראת ספק, hatra'at safek, okay? So here too,
did you really do an איסור? issur? Did you really ingest three
forbidden כזיתים? kezeitim? Like yeah. But you're not going to get, you
know, not, you're not going to get punished because of the circumstances
somehow is that, you know, each איסור issur was מבטל mevatel the
other איסור. issur. And even though you never got out of the
world of איסור, issur, the same way when you do an איסור
issur and we just couldn't pinpoint that you were doing the עבירה
aveirah at the time, that saved you, here because we can't pinpoint
which איסור issur to pin on you, it also saves you. But
it's not a real case of התראת ספק. hatra'at safek. That's what
I would like to interpret the גמרא. Gemara. רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafot want to interpret this more literally and that gives them a
real headache because where's the doubt? Where's the ספק? safek? So the
way רש"י Rashi explains it is he explains it any point, I
gave the example of a blender. But if you don't give the
example of the blender, if you give the example that I put
all of those three pieces of meat in my mouth at the
same time and I start chewing, so then the point is where
exactly is the mixture in my mouth? Right? I mean, you know,
if you imagine, right,
actually for רש"י, Rashi, the funny thing for רש"י Rashi is and
for תוספות Tosafot is mostly the way they wind up explaining it,
it doesn't even have to be three things, it's even only two
things that are in your mouth is enough to say you're פטור
patur because where they're being pushed because of the גמרא Gemara about
התראת ספק. hatra'at safek. So if I've got here the פיגול pigul
and I've got here the נותר, notar, they really say this even
with only two things, okay, and here it is, I'm chewing them
in my mouth, okay.
I've got the big, big picture of, I don't know what I'm
doing here, let's see, where would my mouth be in this picture?
I don't know. I don't know. Okay, there I am, I'm chewing.
Like some monster. Anyway, I'm chewing it in my mouth, okay,
which one am I חייב chayav for? Because here there's exactly one
כזית. kezayis. So in order to know,
a כזית kezayis of both of them together?
A כזית kezayis of each of them by itself, okay. But in
the overlap, the part that's being chewed together, okay, one of them
is more than the other. And the one that's more than the
other is the one I'm חייב chayav for. If in this overlap,
there's more פיגול, pigul, then the פיגול pigul is מבטל mevatel the
נותר, notar, and I have a full כזית kezayis of פיגול, pigul,
and I'm חייב chayav on פיגול, pigul, but I'm not חייב chayav
on נותר, notar, because there's not a full כזית. kezayis. Some of
it was בטל. batel? If however the נותר notar is more, then
I have a full כזית kezayis of נותר notar and I'm חייב
chayav for נותר, notar, okay, but I don't have a full amount
of פיגול pigul and I'm פטור pattur from פיגול. pigul. So because
part of it is mixed up in my mouth, part is not,
part is בטל, Batel since I don't know which of those two
is בטל, batel, so therefore it's התראת ספק. hatra'as safeik. That's the
way רש"י Rashi explained it. It has nothing to do with the
fact that there are three of them, okay? It has to do
with the fact that there's a mixture and you don't know which
one wins out, which one is the majority. All right, so תוספות
Tosafos has three other explanations, fine, we're moving on. The biggest חידוש
chiddush is though איסורין מבטלין זה את זה. issurin mevatlin zeh es
zeh. You don't need היתר, heter, okay, that as long as you
have enough נבילה, neveilah, that's מבטל mevatel נבילה. neveilah. Okay, yes Michael.
Wait, but these are the נותר notar and פיגול pigul
these things are different, right?
They're all כרת. kareis.
So why can't I just say don't eat that because it's a
כרת-able kareis offense?
Right, that's what תוספות Tosafos is sort of bothered by, according to
רש"י's Rashi's explanation, that the case of התראת ספק hatra'as safeik is
at the time I don't even know you're doing an עבירה. aveirah.
Here I know you're doing an עבירה, aveirah, I just don't know
which one. So whatever, so תוספות Tosafos gives a whole other explanation
to the גמרא. Gemara. Look at תוספות. Tosafos. We're moving on. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: מתיב רבא. Masiv Rava. Now
we're going to focus on the big חידוש was that איסור issur
is מבטל mevatel איסור. issur. But we're going to focus on the
point that wait, it's just a simple majority? Is a majority enough?
Or you know, what about taste? Okay, so מתיב רבא. Masiv Rava.
So רבא Rava asked: עשה עיסה מן החיטין ומן האורז. Assa issah
min hachitin umin ha'orez. You made, you went ahead and you made
a flour, okay, from a mixture of wheat flour and rice flour.
And then you're going to use this to make חלה challah or
to make מצה. matzah. אם יש בה טעם דגן חייבת בחלה. Im
yesh bah ta'am dagan chayaves bechallah.
If it still tastes like, you can still detect the wheat taste,
then it's considered, now you know that something is only considered to
be bread or מצה matzah if it's made from the five species
of grain. So the rice flour would not be considered bread or
מצה. matzah. So even if this is a majority of rice flour,
if the taste of the wheat is detectable, it is considered to
be real bread and you have to separate חלה. challah. So you
see, there's a majority of rice flour, but because the bread can
be, the thing can be tasted, it's really considered present. So how
can you say you go by majority? Here it's enough that it's
tasted to be considered present. So the גמרא's Gemara's ואף על גב
דרובו אורז, ve'af al gav derubo orez, even though the majority is
rice. The גמרא Gemara says מדרבנן. miderabbanan. That's only rabbinic, we're being
strict. But really the wheat flour is בטל. batel So the גמרא
Gemara says one minute: אי הכי אימא סיפא. ee hachi eima seifa.
Look at the end of this משנה. Mishnah The end of the
משנה Mishnah says אדם יוצא בו ידי חובתו בפסח. adam yotzei bo
yedei chovaso bepesach. You can use this for מצה. matzah. Assuming that
you baked it as מצה matzah and not as חמץ. chametz. So,
so if you can use it for מצה, matzah, you can't say
it's only rabbinic. It means that the wheat is really present. So
how can you say you go by majority? It's clear that even
if something is tastable at a דאורייתא de'oraysa level, it's considered really
to be present. Okay, in other places the גמרא Gemara would call
this טעם כעיקר דאורייתא. ta'am ke'ikkar de'oraysa. The taste counts like the
thing
itself, that's טעם כעיקר is like the thing itself, and that's דאורייתא.
de'oraysa. That's a Torah principle. So because it can be tasted, it's
present. So how could you say the פיגול, pigul, נותר, notar, and
טמא tamei all become בטל? batel. רוב rov shouldn't be enough. So
the גמרא's Gemara's answer is a very simple distinction. אלא מין בשאינו
מינו בטעמא, מין במינו ברובא. Ella min b'sheino mino beta'ama, min bemino
beruba.
Okay, if it is the taste of, if it is like and
unlike, meat and meat getting mixed up, so there's nothing to be
detected. There's no taste. So that's why we go by majority. And
that's the פיגול, pigul, נותר, notar, and טמא. tamei. And that's why
one of them eradicates the other one or whatever because it's all
meat. So all meat, you go by majority. Okay, whereas rice flour
and wheat flour, they're different things and they taste different, so that's
where we say if the thing can be tasted it is still
present. Okay, meaning there's really just one rule. The rule is if
it can be tasted. Well when you're dealing with foods, again when
you're dealing with blood on the מזבח mizbe'ach it goes more by
sight. But at least when you're dealing with foods, the rule is
if it can be tasted it's still present. Okay? So in some
cases it can't be tasted because you're dealing with all things that
all taste the same. But in cases
where it can be tasted, it is present. Now, a question that
ראשונים rishonim ask that I'm just going to... going to put out
there you know is okay one minute so the flour is still
present but the flour I'm now tasting this delicious מצה Matzah it's
90% rice 10% flour I can detect the flour taste okay why
isn't it yes why yes why isn't it only 10% מצה? Matzah?
Why when I eat one כזית Kezayit did I fulfill my obligation?
Fine the wheat is still present 10% of this is kosher מצה
Matzah the other 90% is not חמץ Chametz but it's not kosher
מצה Matzah it's קטניות Kitniyot so why do I fulfill
whichever you can't eat
whatever why do I fulfill my Torah obligation?
Okay so so some ראשונים Rishonim want to use want to make
proof from this that it's not only that the thing is still
present but that it defines the entirety okay that is not at
all פשוט Pashut Michael okay so most ראשונים Rishonim don't say that
most ראשונים Rishonim say no it's only 10% מצה Matzah this is
90% it's only 10% present the hekesh would be let's say I
have kosher meat 10% of חזיר mixed up and I eat a
כזית Kezayit do I get lashes? Did I eat a כזית Kezayit
of חזיר? The חזיר was tasted throughout but only as a minority
taste does the whole כזית Kezayit of meat turn into חזיר? So
some want to say from the מצה Matzah example that the answer
is yes the majority say no the majority say you only ate
a tenth of a כזית Kezayit of חזיר and in the case
of מצה Matzah and חמץ Chametz and whatever and bread that's a
different story okay because there it's about the identity of the whole
thing as bread it's not a הלכה Halacha that you have to
eat wheat the הלכה Halacha is that you have to eat bread
or that you have to eat מצה Matzah there's just a separate
point that we normally define מצה Matzah as coming from the five
grains so there if a percentage of it is still wheat that
defines the whole thing as bread that defines the whole thing as
מצה Matzah okay but that's very different when the issue is you've
got to eat חזיר to get lashes and I did not eat
a כזית Kezayit of חזיר I only ate a tenth of a
כזית Kezayit of חזיר but that is worth noting here the idea
that it's not just that the thing is present at least in
this case of the מצה Matzah and the חלה Challah it seems
to transform the entire thing yes
if you were to choose to address this I'm interested because you're
saying that you know it's basically now המוציא Hamotzi but I thought
in general Sephardim are very strict with this that if you add
other stuff to it you don't make המוציא Hamotzi on it
no that has to do with צורת הפת Tzurat Hapat that does
with other things in this I mean okay so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this מין במינו כמין בשאינו מינו Min be-mino k'min
b'sheino mino
now the גמרא Gemara asks a really good question which gets back
to our משנה Mishnah which seems to say this this idea that
violates the normal rules because our משנה Mishna says
if it is blood and wine you pretend that the wine is
water in order to use this blood on the altar which means
that we look at a מין במינו Min be-mino mixture right like
and like it's sort of like and like blood and wine I
mean they're not exactly the same but for our purposes they look
the same okay and you look at it as if they're different
in order to be lenient so you look at מין במינו Min
be-mino like it's אינו מינו eino mino, like it's blood and water
to be lenient now it's one thing to say that to be
strict right we discussed this before but if the general principle is
that like things are בטל ברוב Batel b'rov right which is what
we just said with ריש לקיש Reish Lakish the meats or whatever
are בטל ברוב Batel b'rov right how come our משנה Mishna, allows
you to look at them as different things to say there's no
ביטול bittul and to even be lenient okay so that certainly seems
to say that we even when they're the same we're going to
apply rules the rule as if they're different and if we say
it to be lenient we should say it to be strict which
is an excellent question so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says
מין במינו כמין בשאינו מינו Min be-mino k'min b'sheino mino why not
look at the case of like and like meat and meat as
like and unlike and say it's still a problem here and you're
still חייב Chayav okay how do I know you do that because
you do it even to be lenient דתנן Ditnan we taught in
our משנה נתערב ביין if it got mixed up in wine the
blood and wine רואין Ro'in אותו כאילו הוא מים you look at
the wine as if it's water so מאי לאו רואין אותו ליין
כאילו הוא מים Mai lav ro'in oto l'yayin k'ilu hu mayim doesn't
this mean you look at the wine like it's water and you're
lenient and you look at the blood as if it's present so
even when it's things that are מין במינו min bemino, you look
at it as if it's different things to
say אינו מין במינו Eino min b'mino
well it's enough מינו Mino for our purposes that they look the
same okay maybe you can make that
I just had a question about the the like the tool of
being able to say even though it's one thing let's look at
it as if it's another why why are you focusing on the
מין במינו min bemino, aspect of it because he's going to say
let's ignore the fact that it's wine and treat it like
what right okay I don't think that that that's fine I mean
תוספות Tosafot gets into the fact that technically it's not מינו I
don't that point that exact distinction is not relevant right now let
me get back to that but the point is still the same
it's a principle where we should say ביטול bitul. but we're going
to look at it as something else and say in an alternate
situation it wouldn't be בטל and it's still present and if we're
going to so you want to say it that way we could
say the emphasis on רואין ro'in okay and therefore if that's true
So there to be lenient, it should be true by the meat
and meat also to be strict. Okay? So מאי לאו רואין ro'in
אותו לדם כאילו מים *mai lav roin oso l'dam k'ilu mayim*, you
look at the blood, I'm sorry, מאי לאו רואין ro'in אותו ליין
כאילו מים *mai lav roin oso l'yayin k'ilu mayim*. You look at
the wine like it's water in order to say the blood is
still present. So the Gemara says: לא *lo*, no, רואין ro'in אותו
לדם כאילו הוא מים *roin oso l'dam k'ilu hu mayim*. This is
so not the פשט *pshat* of the Mishnah. No, what it means
is if a drop of blood falls into wine, you look at
it like the blood was water and it's immediately בטל *batel*. So
it's actually saying the opposite. It's saying like you know, it's saying
which is not at all פשט *pshat* of the Mishnah. If the
blood falls into the wine, the blood is בטל *batel*, it's like
the blood was water. So the Gemara says: No, give me a
break. אי הכי בטל מיבעי ליה *ee hachi batel mibaei lei*. Let
the Mishnah just say if the blood fell in wine it's בטל
*batel*. Okay? ועוד תניא רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר *v'od tanya Rabbi
Yehuda omer*, we taught a baraita. Rabbi Yehuda says: רואין ro'in. אותו
כאילו יין אדום *roin oso k'ilu yayin adom*. We're going to see
in a case, this isn't our case, it's another case about about
טבילה tevilah *tvilah* and something that has in it in it sort
of like white wine, a vessel had white wine it was put
in a מקוה mikvah *mikvah* and it should have been בטל *batel*
and Rabbi Yehuda says whatever, you look at it as if it's
red wine. Okay? אם דהה מראהו כשר ואם לאו פסול *im dehah
marehu kasher v'im lav pasul* and if it like a you know,
if it if it if it fades it's כשר *kasher*, if it
doesn't fade it's פסול *pasul*. So clearly רואין ro'in. *roin* here means
to make it still present. Okay? So we do have this principle
of רואין ro'in *roin* that in a case where it should not
be present because it's all looks the same or whatever, we're going
to say רואין ro'in *roin* in order to make it present. So
we're going to explain this context in a minute. So the Gemara
says: תנאי היא *tannai hi*. It's a debate of Tannaim and now
we're going to quote the baraita that we referenced. כדתניא *k'detanya*, so
here's the baraita we just referenced a line ago. כלי *kli*,
so you have a bucket שיש בו יין לבן *sheyesh bo yayin
lavan*. It's got white wine in it. או חלב *o chalav* or
milk. והטבילו vehitbilo, *v'hitbiloh* and you immerse it in a מקוה *mikvah*.
So now if you immerse it in a מקוה *mikvah*, the water
of the מקוה *mikvah* has to get inside the vessel. So can
we look at but the stuff in the vessel now is not
water of a מקוה *mikvah*, but it sort of it looks like
it, it's easy to get mixed up and it will easily lose
its identity right because it's all very light colored liquid. So can
we look at it like once the water starts going into the
bucket, can we look at but some of this is still wine,
can we look at it like there's all water in the bucket
and the bucket's been immersed in the water? You got the idea?
So the point is white wine or milk getting mixed in inside
the bucket getting mixed in water. When does it stop being wine
and start being water? That's the question. Got it? Okay. So הולכין
אחר הרוב *holchin achar harov*. You go by the majority. If the
majority in the bucket is water, then it's all water because again
we're not saying oh but you can still detect the wine, why
can you not detect the wine? Because it all looks the same.
Got it? So since it all looks the same, you go by
majority. Everybody see that? Okay. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר *Rabbi Yehuda
omer*. No. רואין ro'in. אותו כאילו יין אדום *roin oso k'ilu yayin
adom*. You look at the wine like it's red wine. אם דהה
מראהו כשר *im dehah marehu kasher*. If it will become pale.
To what degree pale? But presumably pale enough that it really all
looks like water presumably, then it's כשר *kasher*. ואם לאו פסול *v'im
lav pasul*. If not it's פסול *pasul*. So now here Rabbi Yehuda
uses the idea of רואין ro'in, *roin* to be strict. This is
like my drop of טרייף *traif* chicken soup falls in my כשר
*kasher* chicken soup. Had it been חזיר *chazer* it could be tasted.
So even if it's chicken it's a problem. Okay? So here Rabbi
Yehuda says the same thing. You want to say it's all כשר
*kasher* because you can't it's all there's a majority of water and
you can't detect the wine. I'm going to treat it like the
wine was red and say had the wine been able to be
detected it would still be present. So it's still present here. So
that's using רואין ro'in *roin* to be strict. Okay? So nobody has
a problem using רואין ro'in. *roin* to be strict. We do it
all the time by forbidden food mixtures. The חידוש *chiddush* was that
our Mishnah said רואין ro'in? *roin* to be lenient. Okay? But now
what we have is the following, okay? We've got the idea of
bucket with the wine, okay? With the wine, okay? That where Rabbi
Yehuda says רואין ro'in
*roin*, okay? And he's being strict in terms of whether it works
for the
מקוה *mikvah*. That's case number one. Case number one is you've got
the case of the three איסורין *issurin* of the Reish Lakish, okay?
And he says בטל *batel* and no רואין ro'in *roin*. You don't
say רואין *roin*, okay? Even to be, okay? And then you have
case number two of our case of the of the Mishnah which
is the drop of wine into like into all of this wine
here. Not wine, blood
into
wine.
And you say רואין *roin* to be lenient. Okay? So the Gemara's
question is, okay? How come Reish Lakish here's רואין *roin*, no רואין
*roin*, רואין *roin*. Okay? How come Reish Lakish does not Say רואין
is not bothered with it, so it means like you look at
them all as the same, I mean they're all the same, whatever,
you allowed ביטול bitul, to work ברוב. berov. Here we say רואין
even to be lenient, even to put the stuff on the altar.
We're not going to allow, and we're not, so this seems like
רואין is a real תורה Torah principle, that you look at as
if it's, as if it's different. And if we use it to
be lenient, we should certainly use it, you know, to be strict,
right? And to say that you've eaten something forbidden. So גמרא Gemara
says here, well here there's a debate. Here רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says רואין by this case about the, about the, about the white
wine, okay, at least he says רואין to be strict, and the
rabbis say you don't say רואין. So what we're going to say
is, it's a debate of whether you say רואין. So רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says רואין and we're going to say presumably whether to
be strict or to be lenient. Okay? And the חכמים Chachamim say
you don't say it. So we're not going to distinguish between strict
and lenient, okay, we're going to say either there's a principle that
you always look at it as if it's different or you don't
look at it as if it's different. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
who's prepared to look at it to be different, even though here
he does it to be lenient, here he'll look at it to
be different, here he does it to be strict, here he'll look
at it as different to be lenient. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda,
is of the position that you look at things as if they're
different, and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is of the position that you
don't look at things as if they're different. So we're making it
a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. Okay, but what still hasn't been explained
is there's a huge difference between being strict here and saying the
טבילה doesn't work and saying you here look at the thing as
present even to make the קרבן korban kosher. Okay, but for the
גמרא Gemara to answer these problems, the גמרא Gemara is basically saying
that it is a debate, either you say רואין in all cases,
whether strict or lenient, or you don't say them.
Okay, it's slightly strange because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in our משנה
is
not the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma also. Exactly, exactly. Okay, although you
could say, and the
גמרא, Gemara, that's why they didn't get that, like you suggested, but
they all agree that in the קולא kula case, in קרבנות, Korbanot,
רואין. Right?
Right? And תוספות Tosafot is going to say in the end that
it's funny, the גמרא Gemara never fully resolves all of it because
it doesn't look at the broad, you know, sort of scope of
הלכה, halacha, where you know, where we sort of look at things
when they're the same as if they are בטל, but דרבנן derabbanan
they're not or whatever. תוספות Tosafot is basically just going to say,
like, you can't account for why in some areas we look at
it this way, some areas that way, we'll get to that in
תוספות Tosafot later. Okay, but at this stage this is what the
גמרא Gemara is saying. And you know, and it's correct. In our
משנה, okay, it sounds like this isn't רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda. but
we're saying the idea of looking at things that are same as
if they're different, רואין, is a רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda position whether
strict or lenient, and there's another position which is we don't say
it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. רמי היא. Remi hi. I'll ask you. דלי שהוא מלא רוקין,
Dli shehu male rokin, a,
a bucket filled with spit, okay, והטבילו,
and you immerse it, כאילו לא טבל, ke'ilu lo taval, it's not
good. Now רש"י Rashi says, we're going to bracket the spit case,
not just because it's a little gross, but because רש"י Rashi says
that spit is really, you didn't have to say filled with spit.
Even if there's just a little bit of spit on it, spit
is a חציצה. chatzitzah. Spit, you know, it prevents, it's thick, it's
not, you don't look, you can't look at it as if it's
water, you look at it as some extraneous surface thing, and therefore
even a little bit is a חציצה chatzitzah and it's a problem.
So let's just bracket the spit case. Okay, we're going to focus
on the next part.
Now, מי רגלים, Mei raglayim, this bucket is filled with urine, רואין
אותו כאילו הן מים. ro'in oto ke'ilu hen mayim.
So first we're going to go with our גרסא. geirsa. You look
at it as if it's water. Why do you look at it
as if it's water? Meaning it's totally kosher. Why? Because רש"י Rashi
says it's not even so much you look at it as if
it's water. It's really, it is water. רש"י Rashi says urine, maybe
the very fact that you use the word מי רגלים, mei raglayim,
like leg water, whatever, but urine he says הלכתית halachically is considered
a water, is considered to be like water. So actually technically you
could have a מקוה out of urine. Okay, disgusting I know. So
actually maybe not because it's not, it's not directly, it's not natural,
it's told in a different way, it's מים שאובים, mayim she'uvim, I
don't know. Anyway, so רש"י Rashi would say anyway that the point
would be that the רואין here is a very different רואין. It
just means like, okay, it's kosher because technically that's water. All right.
מלא מי חטאת, Male mei chatat, now if it's filled with חטאת
chatat liquid,
even though that's also water, because it's significant and has this weighty
status, we're not going to treat it סתם stam like water. We're
going to need to do ביטול bitul in order to consider it
like you have normal מקוה water here. Okay, so this is actually
harder to do, to use than the urine. Okay, עד שירבו מים
על מי חטאת. ad sheyirbu mayim al mei chatat. You have to
have a majority of kosher water. Now what's the problem here? Fine,
it's all the same. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאן שמעת ליה
דאית ליה רואין, רבי יהודה. Man shamat leh de'it leh ro'in, Rabbi
Yehuda. Who holds of רואין? רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda Because here it
says you look at the urine as if it's water. Well the
רואין phrase is a רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda phrase. Now you should
all be jumping up at me and saying what do you mean?
The רואין of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda of this discussion is when
things are the same you look at them like they're different. Here,
the way רש"י *Rashi* explains it, you look at urine like it's
water just means that that's the halakhic status of urine, is that
it's water. So that's why you've got another תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* because
he says I don't begin to understand why this, the way רש"י
*Rashi* reads this, why this רואין *roin* has anything to do with
the other רואין *roin*. Okay, but let's go with רש"י *Rashi* for
the time. So we're going to assume because of the phrase used
by urine even though it's a completely different application, that we're talking
that this משנה *Mishnah* is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*, okay?
So if it's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*, and now you
get to the case of the מי חטאת mei chattat *Mei Chatat*
וקתני דסגי ליה ברובא *ve-katani de-sagi lei be-ruba*. Now you get to
the case at the end where you have מי חטאת mei chattat
*Mei Chatat* with water and majority is enough. Well, why is majority
enough? For רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*, right, even though it's
the same, water and water, you should look at the מי חטאת
mei chattat *Mei Chatat* like it's red wine. Everybody gets that? So
if we can assume this משנה *Mishnah* is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
*Rabbi Yehuda* because of the urine line, although that doesn't seem to
make any sense, okay, if it's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*,
why does the מי חטאת chattat *Mei Chatat* and the water go
by רוב *rov*? For רבי Rebbi. יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* you should never
go by רוב *rov*. For רבי Rebbi, יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* you should
always look at same things as if they're different and as if
it's red wine and it should not be okay. That's the גמרא
*Gemara*'s question. So אמר אביי *Amar Abaye*, אביי *Abaye* says, לא קשיא
*lo kashya*, it's not difficult. הא דידיה הא דרביה *Ha didey ha
d'rabey*. One is his own position and the other is his rebbe's
position. רואין *Roin* is his rebbe's position. Here where you go by
רוב *rov*, it's his position. Why is רואין *roin* his rebbe's position?
דתניא *De-tanya*, רבי Rebbi, יהודה אומר משום רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel, *Rabbi
Yehuda omer mishum Rabban Gamliel*, because here we're going to show you
what his rebbe's position is. אין דם מבטל דם *Ein dam mevatel
dam*, blood does not מבטל *mevatel* blood, that's like in our case,
right, about using it for what do you call it, for to
put blood on the מזבח *mizbeach*. אין רוק מבטל רוק *Ein rok
mevatel rok*. What would be a case of spit? Let's say you
have a spit of a מצורע *metzora*, or of a זב *zav*
getting mixed up with the spit of a כשר *kosher* person. So
it's all still considered present. ואין מי רגלים מבטלים מי רגלים *Ve-ein
mei raglayim mevatlin mei raglayim*, urine, similarly you could say urine of
a טהור *tahor* person getting mixed up with urine of a זב
*zav*. Okay, מין במינו *min b'mino* is not בטל *batel*. That's the
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* of our משנה *Mishnah*, okay? So therefore, so
now what does that have to do with this issue? So רש"י
*Rashi* says, because here actually it's strange. Here you have the water
of the חטאת *chatat* being בטל *batel* in the water of the
מקווה mikvah *mikveh*. So what רש"י *Rashi* says is the following. This
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* here, okay, where you got the white wine
and the water or whatever. So רש"י *Rashi* here and this maybe
a ביסל *bissel* is what you were saying before, is that this
is not מין במינו *min b'mino*. They all look the same, but
they're not really the same. It's wine and water. So the principle
מין במינו *min b'mino* is not בטל *batel* is not relevant to
this case. So this is the רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* that says
that goes like his rebbe. And he says like this: Look, my
rebbe, רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*, holds that מין במינו *min b'mino* is
not בטל *batel*. That's the position I said in the משנה *Mishnah*.
So in this case of white wine and water, it really,
it's really אינו מינו eino mino, *eino mino* and it should be
בטל *batel*, but I come from a tradition that more resists ביטול
bitul *bittul* because even by מין במינו *min b'mino* we don't have
ביטול bitul. *bittul* at all. And maybe this is a ביסל *bissel*
like מין במינו *min b'mino* also because it all looks the same.
So because I come from this tradition that resists ביטול bitul. *bittul*,
I'm going to say here, I'm going to look at the white
wine like it's red in order to make it harder for ביטול
bitul. *bittul* to occur. Okay? So that's why I'm going to say
it here. Okay, now it doesn't exactly explain here why we're lenient,
but we can sort of, but I don't know exactly how we
could say it. Since I come from a tradition that resists ביטול
*bittul*, I guess it doesn't matter whether it's lenient or whether it's
strict. Because when רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* resists ביטול *bittul*, sometimes that's
lenient. Blood and blood allows for a leniency. Okay? So you get
it, if this is all from the position of מין במינו לא
בטל min bemino lo batel, *min b'mino lo batel*, right, this is,
this is his rebbe's position. It means that generally we resist ביטול
*bittul*. So these cases of blood in wine and white wine in
water are really אינו מינו *eino mino*. Got it? So really ביטול
*bittul* is possible. But because we come from, I come from this
tradition that resists ביטול *bittul*, I'm going to actually say here too,
we're going to read it in a way that makes ביטול *bittul*
harder, whether to be strict or whether to be lenient. So this
is really אינו מינו *eino mino*, so the possibility of ביטול *bittul*
is there, but because I generally resist ביטול *bittul* in a מין
במינו *min b'mino* case, I'm going to resist ביטול *bittul* here too.
And anyway both these cases look a ביסל *bissel* like מינו *mino*
because they all look the same anyway. So I'm going to look
at it as if it's different in order to make it harder
to do ביטול *bittul*. So this is the position of his rebbe,
and where he says by the case of the water of the
חטאת *chatat* that it is בטל *batel*, that's his own position. Okay,
you got it? So that's how we're basically explaining it, ignoring the
idea of the urine and the רואין *roin* and why we say,
and I'm not going to bother you with תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*'s explanation.
I'll just tell you that תוספות *Tosafot* has a different גירסא *girsa*.
תוספות *Tosafot*'s גירסא *girsa* instead of instead of רש"י'ס *Rashi's* גירסא *girsa*
מי רגלים רואין כאילו הן מים *mei raglayim roin ke-ilu hen mayim*,
תוספות *Tosafot*'s גירסא *girsa*... says מי רגלים רואהו כאילו הוא דם or
כאילו הוא יין k'ilu hu yayin I think. Okay? So that תוספות'ס
Tosafot's גרסא gersa of you look at the urine like it's wine
is a classic רואה. ro'eh. You look at it as something that
is radically different. All right? So that leads תוספות having a whole
different explanation. Okay? So our גרסא gersa of you look at the
urine like it's water, it's not the classic use of רואה. ro'eh.
תוספות says you look at the urine like it's wine, it is.
But anyway, this גרסא gersa is that it's not. So for whatever
reason we're assigning this like רבי יהודה and then we're saying so
does רבי יהודה allow ביטול ברוב bitul berov or doesn't allow ביטול
ברוב? bitul berov? And it says it depends if you ask him
or you ask his רבי. According to his רבי, רבן גמליאל, מין
במינו לא בטל, so generally resists ביטול. And since that position generally
resists ביטול, when it looks the same even though it's אינו מינו,
we're going to emphasize create look at רואה, ro'eh, pretend they're different
in order to make it and to say that it's not going
to be בטל so
easy.
So what's Rabbi Yehuda's רואה ro'eh example? Only מין בשאינו...
Right, the only case of
רבי יהודה would say רואה ro'eh in this approach would be a
מין באינו מינו min be'eino mino that looks the same. When looks
matter. Right. So okay, so because if it's really מין במינו, then
you don't need רואה ro'eh because it's just never בטל. And if
it's מין באינו מינו min be'eino mino that looks different, you don't
need רואה ro'eh because they really are different. The only case you
need רואה ro'eh is the case that falls between the two. That
it's אינו מינו, so ביטול should be possible, but because it looks
the same ביטול isn't happening, and because it looks the same but
excuse me, but it looks the same and he's going to say
since they're you know we're going to look at them as if
they're more significantly different to prevent ביטול. So let me just read
one more answer. Okay. רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava says, בדלי
שתוכו טהור וגבו טמא עסקינן. bidli she'tocho tahor vegabbo tamei askinan. What
no,
the reason here רבי יהודה generally holds of רואה ro'eh to prevent
ביטול. Why by the bucket of מי חטאת water does he not
say you have to say that? Because this bucket is not really
totally טמא. tamei. It's only טמא tamei on the outside, not on
the inside, which is a pretty good trick because there's טומאת משקין,
tum'at mashkin, טומאה tum'ah of liquids which are rabbinic or whatever, so
basically sometimes can cause vessels to only be טמא tamei on the
outside, not the inside. So since this vessel is only טמא tamei
on the outside, not the inside, you really don't care that it's
filled with מי חטאת on the inside, because the מקווה mikvah water
doesn't have to get on the inside. But nevertheless, דסגי להו בכל
דהו, desaggi lehu bechol dahu, דמדינא דסגי להו בכל דהו, demidina desaggi
lehu bechol dahu, really it's enough that a little water gets on
the inside. Why do you need a little water to get on
the inside? Because in order to make sure the water got all
over the external surfaces, you need a little bit to get inside.
Okay. ורבנן הוא דגזרו בהו, verabbanan hu degazru behu, דילמא חייס עלייהו
ולא מטביל ליה. dilma chayis aleihu velo matbil lei. The רבנן Rabbanan
said, we're not going to let you just focus on the outside
because you need to get a little inside because if because you're
going to be afraid to get a little water inside. Why you
going to be afraid to get a little water inside? Because you
have this precious מי חטאת in your bucket. Okay? And therefore you're
not going to fully immerse the bucket in order to get the
full outside surrounded by water. So because of that we're going to
tell you uh-uh buddy, you've got to get actually majority of מקווה
mikvah water into the bucket. Okay? But really technically you don't need
any מקווה mikvah water in the bucket. Okay? וכיון דאיכא ריבוייא לא
צריך, vekeivan de'ika ribuya lo tzarich, and we say you got to
get the inside of the bucket immersed as well, it's enough that
it's the majority. But technically speaking, you don't even need the inside
immersed at all. And that's why here we're we will allow it
that the majority is kosher water. So this answer basically is רבי
יהודה forget his רבי, forget tying it into מין במינו, רבי יהודה
always holds of רואה, ro'eh, the reason he doesn't hold of רואה
ro'eh in this case of חטאת water is because you really don't
need the מקווה water to get in the bucket anyway. Okay? But
generally רבי יהודה is of the position of רואה, ro'eh, which whether
to be lenient or whether to be strict, and even if things
look the same, you look at it as if they're different in
order to prevent ביטול. All right, and we will continue with this
discussion tomorrow. Yes.